Guide to the Hillhouse Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
After graduation he became a victim of severe chronic dyspepsia, and fell into a state of physical and mental depression. He was elected to a tutorship in College in 1812, and would have succeeded to the office in 1814, had he not declined. In the hope that Change of scene and of climate and the excitement of foreign travel might benefit him, his father consented to his going abroad, in 1816.
He landed at Bordeaux, traveled through the south of France, tarried a short time in Geneva, and by early fall was settled in Paris, in or near which was his home for the rest of his life.
In his first years there he interested himself actively in efforts for the diffusion of evangelical influences among the French people. A little later, he gave considerable time to the translation of a new work on the forest trees of North America, and in that connection tried to promote the cultivation of the olive in the Southern part of the United States.
About 1823 he set about the composition of a philosophical work, to be entitled. "A Demonstration of the Natural Method in Politics, or, the Political Experience of the United States, applied to Europe," which occupied him for the rest of his life. He withdrew from society, and postponed his return to his family home until his great work should be completed.
In July, 1853, he made an arrangement by which his unimproved real estate in New Haven was transferred to Yale College, in return for an annuity of $1,200; the property was held for many years, but ultimately realized much more than the amount paid to Mr. Hillhouse.
In his lonely life he found his chief pleasure in beneficence to the poor; and when he died on March 14, 1859, in his 68th year, he was sincerely mourned by the peasants of the little village of Eragny, where the event occurred, on the left bank of the Oise, about fifteen miles northwest of Paris.
He was never married. His body was brought to America for burial, in accordance with his own expressed wish.
He left behind him a large collection of manuscripts, but not in condition to be printed.
He printed:
1. Description of the European Olive Tree. [Paris, 1818.] Large 8°, pp. 43 + Pl. [ B. Publ. Harv. Y. C. This article was written for the North American Sylva, by F. A. Michaux, and appears in Mr. Hillhouse's translation of that work, volume 2, PP 156-204.
Another edition is:-
An Essay on the History and Cultivation of the European Olive Tree. Paris, 1820. 8°, pp. 54 + pl. [ B. Publ. M. H. S.
2. A Hymn. In the Christian Spectator, vol. 4, pp. 195-196. New Haven, April, 1822. 8°.
Seven stanzas, of four lines, signed with initials only. See the biographical article on the author, by the Rev. Dr. Bacon, in the New Englander.
3. The Natural Method in Politics, being the abstract of an unpublished work. Paris, 1826.
Said to have been privately printed, in a very small edition.
He was also the author of the following anonymous translation from the French:-
4. The North American Sylva, or a description of the forest trees, of the United States, Canada and Nova Scotia. Considered particularly with respect to their use in the Arts and their introduction into Commerce; to which is added a description of the most useful of the European forest trees. .. By F. Andrew Michaux. Philadelphia and Paris, 1817-1819. 3 vols. 8°.
[Harv. Philad. Libr. Co. U. S.]
About the same date he translated and adapted from the English into French, numerous tracts by Hannah More.
AUTHORITIES.
Dwight Family, ii, 1092. Hist. Biogr. Record, iv, 146. Walworth Magazine, iii, 192. New Englander, Hyde Family, ii, 929. xviii, 557-572. N. Y. Geneal. and
Franklin B. Dexter, Biographical Sketches of the Graduates of Yale College, Vol. VI, 1805-1815 (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1912), pp. 331-333.
* * * * *
JAMES HILLHOUSE (1854-1938), B.A. 1875
Born November 19, 1854, in New Haven, Conn.
Died September 17, 1938, in New Haven, Conn.
Father, William Hillhouse (M.D., New York University 1845; M.A. Hon. Yale 1849), a physician in New Haven; son of Thomas and Anne VanSchaick (TenBroeck) Hillhouse of Watertown, N.Y. Mother, Frances Julia (Betts); daughter of Samuel Rossiter Betts, LL.D. (B.A. Williams 1806), and Caroline Abigail (Dewey) Betts of New York City. Yale relatives include: James A. Hillhouse (BA. 1749) (great-great-uncle); James Hillhouse (B.A. 1773) and William Hillhouse (B.A. 1777) (great-uncles); Francis Betts Hillhouse, '25 (nephew); and John TenBroeck Hillhouse, '69, and Samuel Rossiter Betts, '75 (cousins).
Hopkins Grammar School. Second premium for English composition Sophomore year; philosophical oration appointment Junior and Senior years; Townsend Prize; Commencement speaker; member Class walking club; Kappa Sigma Epsilon, Phi Theta Psi, Psi Upsilon, and Phi Beta Kappa.
Traveled abroad 1875-76; attended Columbia University School of Law 1876-78 (LL.B. 1878); admitted to New York bar as attorney at law 1878 and as counselor at law 1879; in office of Hill [James K.,'54], Wing & Shroudy, New York City, 1878-79; associated with George F. Betts January-September, 1879, with Horatio F. Averill 1879-1880, and with A C. Fransioli 1880-81; managing clerk Chittenden, Townsend [James M., '74] & Chittenden [Horace H., '74] 1881-82 and with Seward, DaCosta & Guthrie 1882-88; engaged in independent practice in New York City 1888-1905; lecturer on parliamentary law and procedure New York University School of Law 1896-97 and professor of law 1897-1899; retired from practice of law in 1905 and had since resided in New Haven; Class secretary for a short time after graduation; member Mayor's Committee on New Haven Tercentenary Celebration and on the Committee for the State of Connecticut; member New York Bar Association, American Bar Association, New Haven Chamber of Commerce, and St. Thomas' Church (Episcopal), New Haven (vestryman since 1919 and member building committee since 1930).
Married October 3, 1894, in New York City, Hildegarde, daughter of Albert and Matilda Livingston (Rogers) Speyers. No children.
Death due to arterial sclerosis of the heart. Buried in Grove Street Cemetery, New Haven. Survived by wife and a brother, Francis Hillhouse, '79 S. Another brother, Charles Betts Hillhouse, '78 S., died December 28, 1937.
In 1931 Mr. Hillhouse gave to the Yale Law Library his law library of 2,400 volumes, including many rare and out of print items.
Yale University Obituary Record, 1938-1939. pp. 14-15.
For charts outlining the genealogical relations of the Hillhouse, Lloyd-Woolsey, and Speyers families, please consult the Genealogical Charts.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Architecture, Domestic -- Designs and plans; Associations, institutions, etc. -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Book collecting; Business; Courtship; Families; Hardware stores -- New York (State) -- New York; Law; Lectures and lecturing; Marriage; Single women; Women; Connecticut -- History; Duluth (Minn.); Europe; France -- Description and travel; New Haven (Conn.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; New Haven (Conn.) -- Social life and customs; Plattsburgh (N.Y.); United States -- Politics and government -- 1789-1815; Account books; Architectural drawings; Commonplace books; Deeds; Scrapbooks; Authors; Book collectors; Lawyers; Politicians; Alexander, E. P.; Betts, George Frederic, 1827-; Betts, Samuel Rossiter, 1854-1931; Blanchard, George R. (George Roberts), 1841-1900; Borland, John; Bowdoin, James; Carmick, E. H.; Clap, Thomas, 1703-1767; Davenport, Theodore, 1792-; Davis, Alexander Jackson, 1803-1892; Dwight, Timothy, 1752-1817; Evarts, Sherman, 1859-1922; Grant, Percy Stickney, 1860-1927; Head, Frazier Davenport, 1853-; Hewit, Nathaniel, 1788-1867; Hewit, Rebecca Woolsey Hillhouse, 1794-1831; Hillhouse Rebecca Woolsey, 1755-1813; Hillhouse, Augustus L. (Augustus Lucas), 1791-1859; Hillhouse, Charles Betts, 1856-1937; Hillhouse, Cornelia Ann Lawrence, d. 1874; Hillhouse, Frances Julia Betts, 1822-1907; Hillhouse, Francis, 1859-; Hillhouse, Hildegarde Speyers, 1866-1942; Hillhouse, Isaphene; Hillhouse, James Abraham, 1730-1775; Hillhouse, James Abraham, 1789-1841; Hillhouse, James, 1754-1832; Hillhouse, James, 1854-1938; Hillhouse, Mary Lucas, 1785-1871; Hillhouse, Sarah L.; Hillhouse, William, 1757-1833; Hillhouse, William, 1820-1906; King, Henry; Kip, William Ingraham, 1811-1893; Law, William H.; Lawrence, Isaac, 1768-1841; Lawrence, William Beach, 1800-1881; Lloyd, James, 1728-1810; Lloyd, James, 1769-1831; Moale, Laura M. Speyers; Moale, Philip Randle, 1867-; Nelson, John, -1734; Perkins, James W.; Pickering, Henry, 1781-1838; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946; Porter, John Addison, 1856-1900; Rogers, Henry Livingston; Semour, Zachariah, 1732-; Sherman, Roger Minott, 1773-1844; Silliman, Benjamin, 1779-1864; Speyers, Albert Willoughby; Speyers, Clarence Livingston, 1863-; Speyers, Selina L.; Strickland, William, 1787-1854; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930; Town, Ithiel, 1784-1844; Van Santvoord, Abraham; Whedon, Charles R.; Whitney, Eli, 1765-1825; Wickes, Thomas Parmelee, 1853-1933; Woolsey, Melancthon Lloyd, 1955-; Woolsey, Theodosia, 1747-1830; Borland family; Hillis family; Lloyd family; Speyers family; Woolsey family; Connecticut. Commissioner of the School Fund; United States. Congress. Senate; Ascension Mission Association; Farmington Canal Company; Sachem's Wood (New Haven, Conn.); Yale University -- History; Yale University -- Students
- CORRESPONDENCE AND DEEDS, 1707-1938; Series I; 5.75 linear feet (14 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged in two sections: Correspondence and Deeds. Each section is arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence
    - 1707-1800 (Box 1, Folder 1-14)
    - 1801-1812 (Box 2, Folder 15-27)
    - 1813-1821 (Box 3, Folder 28-40)
    - 1822-1927 April (Box 4, Folder 41-53)
    - 1827 May-1839 (Box 5, Folder 54-67)
    - 1840-1887 (Box 6, Folder 68-82)
    - 1888-1892 (Box 7, Folder 83-95)
    - 1893-1896 May (Box 8, Folder 96-107)
    - 1896 June-1899 June (Box 9, Folder 108-121)
    - 1899 July-1902 (Box 10, Folder 122-133)
    - 1903-1907 (Box 11, Folder 134-145)
    - 1908-1938 (Box 12, Folder 146-157)
    - undated (Box 13, Folder 158-163)
  - Deeds, 1715; 1752-1887 (Box 14, Folder 164-172)
- JAMES ABRAHAM HILLHOUSE (1730-1775), 1753-1791; Series II; 0.25; (1 box)
  This series is arranged alphabetically by record type.
  - Account books, 1753-1791 (Box 15, Folder 173-174)
- JAMES HILLHOUSE (1754-1832), 1776-1905; Series III; 1 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Account books, 1815-1831 (Box 16, Folder 175)
  - Bills, 1797-1811 (Box 16, Folder 176-177)
  - Daybook of Farmington Canal Company, 1826-1831 (Box 16, Folder 178)
  - Diary, 1776-1777 (Box 16, Folder 179)
  - Estate records
    - Account books, 1840-1866 (Box 16, Folder 180-181)
    - Bills and receipts, 1836-1905 (Box 16, Folder 182)
    - Notebooks, 1795-1876 (Box 16, Folder 183-186)
    - Notebooks, 1861-1864 (Box 17, Folder 187)
    - Receipt book, 1845-1852 (Box 17, Folder 188)
  - Legal and military papers, 1777-1795 (Box 17, Folder 189)
  - Lists of landed property owned, 1798-1831 (Box 17, Folder 190)
  - School fund papers, 1810-1833 (Box 17, Folder 191)
  - Writings, 1779-1830 (Box 17, Folder 192-193)
- WILLIAM HILLHOUSE (1757-1833), 1781-1834; Series IV; 0.25; (1 box)
  - Bills and receipts, 1781-1813 (Box 18, Folder 194)
  - Legal papers, 1797-1819 (Box 18, Folder 195)
  - Notebooks, 1789-1834 (Box 18, Folder 196-197)
- MARY LUCAS HILLHOUSE (1785-1871) Mary Lucas Hillhouse (1785-1871), 1789-1871; Series V; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Account books, 1856-1866 (Box 19, Folder 198)
  - Accounts, 1837-1871 (Box 19, Folder 199-200)
  - Album, 1789 (Box 19, Folder 201)
  - Bank book, 1837-1847 (Box 19, Folder 202)
  - Legal papers, 1833-1867, undated (Box 19, Folder 203)
  - Notebooks, 1835-1862 (Box 19, Folder 204-205)
  - Obituaries, 1871 (Box 19, Folder 206)
  - Scrapbooks, 1817-1868 (Box 20, Folder 207-208)
- JAMES ABRAHAM HILLHOUSE (1789-1841), 1794-1853; Series VI; 3.5 linear feet (9 boxes)
  - Account books, 1811-1848 (Box 21, Folder 209-212)
  - Accounts, 1819-1834 (Box 21, Folder 213)
  - Address books, n. d. (Box 21, Folder 214)
  - Bills and receipts, 1810-1817 (Box 21, Folder 215)
  - Bills and receipts, 1818-1832 (Box 22, Folder 216-222)
  - Bills and receipts, 1832-1836 (Box 23, Folder 223-228)
  - Bills and receipts, 1837-1840 (Box 24, Folder 229-234)
  - Biographical sketch, 1851 (Box 24, Folder 235)
  - Cashbooks, 1820-1853 (Box 25, Folder 236-237)
  - Commonplace books, 1807-1840 (Box 25, Folder 238-239)
  - Commonplace books, 1817-1848 (Box 26, Folder 240-242)
  - Commonplace book, 1807-1840 (Box 27, Folder 243)
  - Estate records, 1841-1853 (Box 27, Folder 244)
  - Ledger, 1823-1840 (Box 27, Folder 245)
  - Legal papers, 1821-1839 (Box 27, Folder 246-249)
  - Notebooks, 1810-1840 (Box 28, Folder 250-258)
  - Scrapbook, 1794-1836 (Box 29, Folder 259)
  - Writings, [1813?]-1814 (Box 29, Folder 260-261)
- JAMES HILLHOUSE AND SON, 1815-1831; Series VII; 3.5 linear feet (7 boxes)
  - Account books, 1815-1822 (Box 30, Folder 262)
  - Bank books, 1815-1816 (Box 30, Folder 263)
  - Bills and receipts, 1816-1821 (Box 30, Folder 264)
  - Daybook, 1815-1816 (Box 30, Folder 265)
  - Daybook, 1816-1817 (Box 31, Folder 266)
  - Daybook, 1817-1821 (Box 32, Folder 267)
  - Daybook, 1821-1831 (Box 33, Folder 268)
  - Inventory book, 1816-1820 (Box 34, Folder 269)
  - Ledger, 1815-1822 (Box 35, Folder 270)
  - Legal papers, 1815-1821 (Box 36, Folder 271)
  - Letterbooks, 1818-1831 (Box 36, Folder 272-274)
- AUGUSTUS LUCAS HILLHOUSE (1791-1859), 1805-1859; Series VIII; 2 linear feet (5 boxes)
  - Bills and receipts, 1817-1858 (Box 37, Folder 275)
  - Calendar of letters, 1815-1837 (Box 37, Folder 275)
  - Commonplace books, 1817-1822 (Box 37, Folder 276-277)
  - Commonplace books, 1827-1829 (Box 38, Folder 278-281)
  - Commonplace books, 1830-1842 (Box 39, Folder 282-284)
  - Commonplace book, 1843-1859 (Box 40, Folder 285)
  - Drawings, Legal papers, 1805-1836 (Box 40, Folder 286)
  - Notebooks, 1817-1821 (Box 40, Folder 287-289)
  - Notebooks, 1805-1825 (Box 41, Folder 290-291)
  - Writings, 1806-1821 (Box 41, Folder 292-95)
- CORNELIA ANN LAWRENCE HILLHOUSE (1802-1874), 1822-1874; Series IX; 0.5; (1 box)
  - Account books, 1848-1874 (Box 42, Folder 296)
  - Bills and receipts, 1850-1869 (Box 42, Folder 297)
  - Cashbook, 1862-1874 (Box 42, Folder 298)
  - Commonplace book, 1822 (Box 42, Folder 299)
  - Legal papers, 1843-1871 (Box 42, Folder 300)
  - Poem, 1831 (Box 42, Folder 300)
  - Hillhouse, John (1817-1882): album, 1846 (Box 42, Folder 301)
- WILLIAM HILLHOUSE (1820-1906), 1832-1905; Series X; 2 linear feet (5 boxes)
  - Account books, 1855-1870 (Box 43, Folder 302)
  - Bills and receipts, 1853-1905 (Box 43, Folder 303-305)
  - Cashbook, 1842-1849 (Box 44, Folder 306)
  - Drawings, n. d. (Box 45, Folder 307)
  - Legal papers, 1861-1893 (Box 45, Folder 308)
  - Medical almanac, 1844, [1849?] (Box 45, Folder 309)
  - Notebooks
    - Chronometers, 1852 (Box 45, Folder 310)
    - Mathematics, 1845-1885 (Box 45, Folder 311-314)
    - Mathematics, 1885-1895 (Box 46, Folder 315-318)
    - Medicine, 1843-1845 (Box 46, Folder 319-320)
    - Mortgages, 1853-1868 (Box 46, Folder 321)
  - Notes: mathematics, 1832-1895 (Box 47, Folder 322-324)
  - Scrapbook: Civil War, 1861-1864 (Box 47, Folder 325)
  - Writings, 1845 (Box 47, Folder 326)
  - Hillhouse, Cornelia (1825-1851)
    - Commonplace book, 1843-1850 (Box 47, Folder 327)
    - Drawings, 1834-1839 (Box 47, Folder 328)
- MARY HILLHOUSE (1828-1874), 1834-1874; Series XI; 0.5; (1 box)
  - Account book, 1872-1874 (Box 48, Folder 329)
  - Autograph book, undated (Box 48, Folder 330)
  - Commonplace book, 1834-1840 (Box 48, Folder 331)
  - Minute book, 1871-1873 (Box 48, Folder 332)
  - Writings, 1871-1873 (Box 48, Folder 333-334)
- ISAPHENE HILLHOUSE (1830-1904), 1835-1941; Series XII; 1 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Bank books, 1876-1893 (Box 49, Folder 335)
  - Commonplace books, 1852-1879 (Box 49, Folder 336)
  - Commonplace book, 1835-1842 (Box 50, Folder 337)
  - Estate records, 1897-1941 (Box 50, Folder 338)
  - Legal and financial papers, 1859-1897 (Box 50, Folder 339)
  - Notebooks, 1878-1889 (Box 50, Folder 340-342)
  - Scrapbooks, 1841-1902 (Box 50, Folder 343-344)
- JAMES HILLHOUSE (1854-1938), 1868-1938; Series XIII; 11 linear feet (26 boxes)
  - Accounts, 1888-1905 (Box 51, Folder 345)
  - Appointment books, 1880-1921 (Box 51, Folder 346-350)
  - Appointment books, 1922-1937 (Box 52, Folder 351-355)
  - Case files
    - William J. Boyle v. Emory Van Tassel, 1890-1891 (Box 53, Folder 356)
    - Chemical National Bank of New York v. National Life Association of Hartford, 1899-1902 (Box 53, Folder 357-358)
    - Charles B. Hillhouse v. Emory Van Tassel, 1889-1895 (Box 53, Folder 359-360)
    - Charles B. Hillhouse v. Emory Van Tassel, 1889-1895 (Box 54, Folder 361-365)
    - Charles B. Hillhouse v. Emory Van Tassel, 1889-1895 (Box 55, Folder 366-372)
    - Charles B. Hillhouse v. Emory Van Tassel, 1889-1895 (Box 56, Folder 373-375)
    - Charles B. Hillhouse v. Emory Van Tassel, 1892-1893 (Box 57, Folder 376)
    - Hillhouse & Day v. Hickox & Cashing, 1886 (Box 57, Folder 377-378)
    - Chas. Hillhouse & F. Hillhouse v. Jas. Day, 1892-1895 (Box 57, Folder 379)
    - Hillhouse v. Day, 1892-1895 (Box 58, Folder 380)
    - Manufacturers Fire and Marine Insurance Co. v. Robert A. Maxwell et. al., 1889-1891 (Box 58, Folder 381-385)
    - Metcalf Land Co., 1895-1896 (Box 59, Folder 386)
    - People of State of New York v. Republican Official Primary Election Inspectors, 1904 (Box 59, Folder 387)
    - Stienhardt & Goldman v. Walker et. al., 1891-1892 (Box 59, Folder 388)
    - Van Leevwen & Michelson Bankrupts, 1903-1904 (Box 59, Folder 389-390)
    - Miscellanea, 1880-1905 (Box 59, Folder 391-392)
    - Miscellanea, 1880-1905 (Box 60, Folder 393-397)
    - Miscellanea, 1880-1905 (Box 61, Folder 398-403)
    - Miscellanea, 1880-1905 (Box 62, Folder 404-409)
    - Miscellanea, 1880-1905 (Box 63, Folder 410-414)
  - Insurance policies, 1893-1908 (Box 64, Folder 415-417)
  - Letterpress copybooks, 1882-1899 (Box 65, Folder 418-420)
  - Letterpress copybooks, 1899-1906 (Box 66, Folder 421-422)
  - Notebooks
    - Latin, undated (Box 67, Folder 423)
    - Law, 1876-1877 (Box 67, Folder 424-428)
    - Law, 1876-1877, undated (Box 68, Folder 429-431)
    - Miscellanea (Box 68, Folder 432-433)
    - Register of causes at law, 1884-1902 (Box 68, Folder 432-433)
  - Notes
    - Books, undated (Box 69, Folder 434)
    - International law, undated (Box 69, Folder 435)
    - Parliamentary procedure, undated (Box 69, Folder 436-438)
    - Points of law, undated (Box 69, Folder 439)
    - Police court, 1894-1895 (Box 69, Folder 440)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 69, Folder 441)
  - Printed material, 1900-1937 (Box 69, Folder 442)
  - School exercises, 1868-1870, undated (Box 69, Folder 443)
  - Scrapbooks, 1899-1903 (Box 70, Folder 444-445)
  - Scrapbooks, 1904-1920 (Box 71, Folder 446-447)
  - Scrapbooks, 1899 (Box 72, Folder 448)
  - Topical files
    - Account books, 1881-1889 (Box 73, Folder 449)
    - Ascension Church, 1890-1933 (Box 73, Folder 450)
    - Ascension Mission Association, 1888-1900 (Box 73, Folder 451-452)
    - Committee of Seventy, 1894 (Box 73, Folder 453)
    - Library accessions, 1896-1911 (Box 73, Folder 454-456)
    - Library accessions, 1912-1938 (Box 74, Folder 457-460)
    - Library catalogues, 1893-1931, undated (Box 74, Folder 461-463)
    - Marine Signal Company, 1864-1879 (Box 75, Folder 464)
    - Religious and charitable organizations, 1899-1919, undated (Box 75, Folder 465-466)
    - Republican politics, 1895-1917, undated (Box 75, Folder 467-473)
    - Yale University, 1895-1916 (Box 76, Folder 474-476)
    - Miscellanea re: railroads, Circa 1876-1897 (Box 76, Folder 477-480)
- CHARLES BETTS HILLHOUSE (1856-1937), 1868-1894; Series XIV; 0.25; (1 box)
  - Appointment book, 1887 (Box 77, Folder 481)
  - Bankbook, 1888 (Box 77, Folder 481)
  - Bills and receipts, 1868, 1887-1888 (Box 77, Folder 482)
  - Legal papers, Circa 1893-1894 (Box 77, Folder 483-484)
  - Notebooks, Circa 1878, 1882 (Box 77, Folder 485)
- HILDEGARDE SPEYERS HILLHOUSE (1866-1942), 1888-1943; Series XV; 0.5; (1 box)
  - Autograph album, 1910-1916 (Box 78, Folder 486)
  - Estate records, 1941-1943, undated (Box 78, Folder 487)
  - Financial records, 1894 (Box 78, Folder 487)
  - Letterbook, 1896-1906 (Box 78, Folder 488)
  - Lists re: Parsifal class, 1903 (Box 78, Folder 489)
  - Music books, 1888-1904 (Box 78, Folder 489)
  - Notebook, notes re: visits to public schools, 1896-1902, undated (Box 78, Folder 490)
  - Notebooks: religious, 1890-1900 (Box 78, Folder 491)
- MISCELLANEOUS PAPERS, 1762-1931; Series XVI; 3.5 linear feet (9 boxes)
  This series is divided into two sections: Papers of ))thers Miscellaneous and Unidentified. The former is arranged alphabetically by name, the latter alphabetically by record type.
  - Papers of others
    - Blanchard, Delia Thompson: diaries, 1871; 1878 (Box 79, Folder 492)
    - Blanchard, George Roberts
      - Correspondence, 1879-1880 (Box 79, Folder 493)
      - Letterpress copybook, 1883 (Box 79, Folder 494)
      - Scrapbook, 1879 (Box 79, Folder 495)
    - Bowen, Sarah Hewit: record book, [ca. 1883-1891] (Box 79, Folder 496)
    - Davis, Alexander Jackson, 1803-1892: Title page for American Rural Residences, Circa 1836 (Box 79, Folder 497)
    - Eliot, Sophia Wasson: album, 1838-1844 (Box 80, Folder 498)
    - Hammon, Jupiter: poem, Essay on Slavery, 1786 (Box 80, Folder 499)
      General
      This item has been transferred to Box 80A, Folder 511A.
    - Hewit, Henry Stewart: legal papers, 1847-1848 (Box 80, Folder 500)
    - Hewit, Nathaniel, 1788-1867: bills and receipts, 1817-1818, 1867 (Box 80, Folder 500)
    - Hewit, Nathaniel Augustus, 1820-1897 (Box 80, Folder 501)
      - Legal papers, 1841, 1844 (Box 80, Folder 501)
      - Poems, 1836-1839 (Box 80, Folder 501)
    - Hewit, Rebecca Woolsey Hillhouse, 1796-1831: obituaries (Box 80, Folder 501)
    - Kip, William Ingraham: article, 1861-1883, undated (Box 80, Folder 502)
    - Metcalf, James W.: manuscript calendar, undated (Box 80, Folder 503)
    - Middlebrooks, John: account book, 1864-1865 (Box 80, Folder 503)
    - North Eastern Railway, England: inventory, [ca. 1849] (Box 80, Folder 504)
    - Robinson, William: manuscript, undated (Box 80, Folder 505)
    - Rogers, Halsey: notebook, undated (Box 80, Folder 506)
    - Rogers, Henry Livingston (Box 80, Folder 507)
      - Estate records, 1913 (Box 80, Folder 507)
      - Notebook: Rogers family genealogy, [ca. 1888-1898] (Box 80, Folder 507)
    - Sigourney, Mary and Andrew: poem, 1834 (Box 80, Folder 508)
    - Silliman, Benjamin, 1779-1864: essay, 1859 (Box 80, Folder 508)
    - Skinner, Aaron Nichols, 1800-1858: miscellaneous, undated (Box 80, Folder 509)
    - Speyers, Matilda Livingston Rogers
      - Legal papers, 1866-1896 (Box 80, Folder 510-511)
      - Notebook, 1857 (Box 80, Folder 511)
    - Hammon, Jupiter: poem, Essay on Slavery, 1786 (Box 80A, Folder 511A)
    - Stowe, Harriet Elizabeth Beecher: manuscript, 1825 (Box 81, Folder 512)
    - Thomson, Maye B.: notebook, 1886 (Box 81, Folder 513)
    - Turner, [daniel?]: prospectus for Susquehannah Coal Company, [ca.1807] (Box 81, Folder 514)
    - Whedon, Charles R.
      - Account books, 1864-1866 (Box 81, Folder 515)
      - Bills and receipts, [ca. 1856-1884] (Box 81, Folder 516-520)
      - Correspondence and miscellaneous papers, 1856-1883, undated (Box 82, Folder 521)
      - Justice Docket record book, 1876-1886 (Box 82, Folder 522)
      - "Justice notes" notebooks, 1880-1885, undated (Box 82, Folder 523-526)
      - Legal papers